Hi! I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 6 of our 10 day Lipreading Challenge,
designed to help you develop
and practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity to
relationships in all areas of your life.
Yesterday, we started with vowels.
There's two reasons to learn about vowels:
there's a vowel in every word in English,
and it's mostly the vowels
that give rise to accents in English.
Here's another thing to know
about vowels:
they have low pitch energy.
So when you're yelling or speaking
loudly, it's mostly the vowel sounds
that are getting louder.
Remember vowels have that
open vocal tract
and that allows you to
get that sound energy out.
Versus with a high-pitched consonant,
the sound energy has to go through the
constriction or the closure.
So for example, for the F or the V sound,
the air has to go through
the constriction of the teeth and the lip.
Try yelling a V.
So if you find that you can hear, but you
can't understand,
it might be because you're mostly hearing the vowel sounds.
Most people with permanent hearing loss have a sloping hearing loss
where the high frequency sounds are most affected.
The low pitch vowels for example, are audible.
But those high pitch consonants, the
ones that can't really be said loudly
because of the closure or constriction,
are the ones that are affected.
So let's look more closely at the long
vowels and the diphthongs
and see how they are formed.
Remember the long vowels
are pronounced the same way they are
said in the alphabet:
A, E, I, O, and U.
For the vowel A,
the lips draw back as in LATE.
For the vowel E,
the lips come back even more,
and the opening
between the lips is narrower, as in BEEF.
For the vowel I, your mouth opens wide
like it would if your physician put a
tongue depressor in your mouth
and asked you to say “AH.” And then as
the sound completes,
the lips come together for the EE.
AH-EE, as in WIFE.
The O sound is pretty easy.
Your lips form a small circle,
as in THOSE.
For the U sound,
your lips thrust forward
and then come close together,
as in FLUTE.
For the diphthong OI,
the lips come forward
to form that small circle O,
and then they come backwards and have a narrow opening
for the EE, BOY.
For the diphthong OW,
also spelled OU, the mouth opens wide
for the AH and then the jaw closes
for the U, AH-OU,
as in the word SHOUT.
The last vowel I'm going to cover is the ER.
The lips round and pucker, as in BERT, or SHIRT.
Let's get some practice lip reading the
long vowels
and diphthongs.
As usual, the answers are written below
the video frame, and as usual,
if you're having difficulty
after you get warmed up
with the first few,
follow the directions
that are written below
on how to make it easier,
and then make sure you come back!
So I'm going to say the sentence silently first,
then I'm going to give you a clue or some context
and then I'll say it silently again.
Are you ready?
Number 1
Your context is this photo:
Number 1 again:
Number 2
The context is: age.
Number 2 again:
Number 3
The context is: exercise.
Number 3 again:
Number 4
The context is:
I'm interested in your book.
Number 4 again:
Number 5
The clue is: It's a gift.
Number 6
And the clue is:
it's about food storage.
Here it is again:
Number 7
And the clue is: baked goods.
Here it is again:
Number 8
and the context is: getting a good seat.
Here it is again:
Number 9
and the context is:
a remedy for pain.
Here it is again:
Number 10
and the context is this photo:
Here's number 10 again:
That's it for vowel practice.
One final interesting thing
about vowels
is that they carry a lot of emotional energy,
such as
OWWW
AWWW?!
OHHHH!
UGH
So what do you think about vowels now?
Any insights?
I'd love to hear about it
or any other aspect of the challenge.
I'd like to hear how you're doing.
Please comment.
Please like my video,
subscribe to my channel,
and especially, share it with others.
It really helps me.
Thank you so much.
I hope you have a
beautiful day.
Bye!